Vivian Amorim

amorim.vivian@icloud.com | +1 202 790-0650

Brazilian National | I possess the USA Employment Authorization Document

SUMMARY

I have a Ph.D. in Economics and have worked for the World Bank for nearly 8 years. I have worked with impact evaluations assessing the effects of public policies on labor and education outcomes; efficiency analysis of public education expenditures; and using microdata to perform simulation of government policies, such as fiscal austerity and trade liberalization policies. I use data analytics and science to model economic issues and create compelling narratives for decision-making. I handle complex and large datasets and conduct advanced statistical and econometric analyses.

EDUCATION

PHD IN ECONOMICS UNIVERSITY OF BRASÍLIA (UNB)

Thesis: Essays on public primary education in Brazil

Completed: 2022

MA IN ECONOMICS UNIVERSITY OF SÃO PAULO (IPE-USP)

Admitted among the top 1% of applicants

Ranked as the best school of economics in Brazil

Thesis: The effects of the decentralization of state-managed schools on students' outcomes

Completed: 2013

BA IN ECONOMICS University of São Paulo (FEA-USP)

Graded among the top 5% of graduates

Completed: 2010

WORK EXPERIENCE

WORLD BANK: GOVERNANCE

SHORT-TERM CONSULTANT

January 2023 - Current | Washington DC, USA

- Conducted wage bill analysis of Indonesia's Central Government. Using microdata at the civil servant level, explored several civil servants' characteristics, such as patterns of wage increases, and gender pay gap. Performed simulations of fiscal austerity measures to provide inputs for the civil servants' reform under analysis by the Indonesian Government. The simulations include scenarios such as freezing salaries, reducing replacement rates, and reducing salary increases due to career progressions.
- Conduced a Literature Review of more than 100 papers that explore the effect of institutional reforms on socioeconomic outcomes, including educational interventions. Explored which of these interventions have a significant impact on students' learning and long-term outcomes. I am focused on papers published in top journals and mostly interventions conducted through randomized control trials.

WORLD BANK: IMPACT EVALUATION UNIT Sep 2019 – March 2020 | Washington DC, USA | EXTENDED-TERM CONSULTANT

- Analyzed the effects of an increase in the minimum employment age, implemented by the federal government in Brazil, on child labor (boys, girls, urban and rural areas). Harmonized several years of the Brazilian household survey, performed data-cleaning, and employed a Regression discontinuity Design. Co-authored the working paper that was published in IZA and will soon be published in the World Bank Economic Review. My code is available in https://github.com/dime-worldbank/child-labor-ban-brazil.
- Studied the impact of a financial literacy intervention (RCT) implemented in 100 schools. Performed the econometric analysis of the channels from which the intervention impacted students' financial skills. Co-authored a working paper that will soon be available in the World Bank Policy Research. My code is available in https://github.com/dime-worldbank/financial-education-brazil.
- Quantified the impacts of school closures on students' learning amid the H1N1 outbreak in Brazil. Combined large administrative datasets to perform a non-experimental evaluation under a difference-in-differences approach. My code is available in https://github.com/dime-worldbank/h1n1-school-closures-sp-2009.
- Designed an impact evaluation of the educational intervention "Brasil na Escola". Power calculations
 of a cluster randomized trial under several assumptions using Stata and Optimum Design. Designed
 the socioeconomic questionnaire and estimated the cost of the intervention. Disseminated the pilot
 design to government officials.
- Quantified the impact of World Bank operations on economic activity under a difference-in-differences approach. Used night-time light data at the village level and harmonized household surveys to measure socioeconomic outcomes. My code and presentations are available in https://github.com/dime-worldbank/IPFspforRs.
- Assessed the impacts of the Kosovo Credit Guarantee Fund on firm productivity, employment, and sales. Disseminated the results to the Ministry of Finance, the Central Bank, and private banks. My contributions are currently being used by the World Bank Office in the dialogue with the banking system to improve the design of policies. My code is available in https://github.com/dime-worldbank/kosovo-kcgf.
- The aforementioned advanced statistical and econometric analyses were conducted using Stata. I was in charge of all data-cleaning, standardized coding, and econometric analysis.
- Supported the preparation of Concept Notes and funding proposals.

WORLD BANK: HUMAN DEVELOPMENT UNIT/GOVERNANCE

CONSULTANT

Jan 2016 – Aug 2019 | Brasília, Brazil

- Employed a Data Envelopment Analysis to assess the efficiency of public education expenditures across more than 5,000 Brazilian municipalities. Disseminated the results at the Conference of the Brazilian Econometric Society. Empirical analyses are available in A Fair Adjustment: efficiency and equity of public spending in Brazil: Volume 1 Overview (English). Washington, D.C.: World Bank Group.
- Explored the inequality in the redistribution of the resources of the most important educational fund (FUNDEB) in Brazil. Collected data on tax revenues at the federal, state, and municipality levels and simulated the decrease in the inequality of the expenditure per student if the redistribution rules of the fund were altered.
- Developed an economic model to assess the impacts of liberalizing trade policy on poverty and inequality rates through labor market and consumption channels. The empirical analysis is available in Chapter 5 of Dutz, Mark A. 2018. Jobs and Growth: Brazil's Productivity Agenda. International Development in Focus. Washington, DC. World Bank Group.
- Designed a socioeconomic questionnaire to evaluate women's participation in household finances and the incidence of violence against them. Led the training of in-field enumerators on the importance of proper data collection and showcased a pilot questionnaire in villages.

- Performed the diagnosis of the Secondary Education system in Brazil and identification of the main challenges of the Government's proposed reform.
- Developed an economic model using wage-bill microdata to estimate public sector expenditure growth. My code allows the simulation of several austerity measures that are presented to government officials in order to help the formulation of policies to guarantee fiscal sustainability. Disseminated the results to policymakers. The Brazilian Country Office has applied this standardized coding to several states. The code has also been run in Honduras, Uruguay, and Indonesia.
- The aforementioned data-cleaning and statistical and econometric analyses were conducted in Stata using several large administrative datasets, such as the Education Census, Demographic Census, Household Survey, Household Budget Survey, and public sector wage bill.

INTER-AMERICAN DEVELOPMENT BANK: LABOR MARKETS UNIT

CONSULTANT

Apr 2014 - Dec 2015 | Brasília, Brazil

- Championed statistical and econometric analysis of labor markets and gender inequality. Provided inputs to IADB technical reports and discussions with researchers and policymakers.
- Partnered with the Brazilian Ministry of Labor to study and design public policies aimed to increase the efficiency of public employment and decrease the percentage of informal workers. Worked closely with government officials and secretaries of labor.
- Led the design of informational videos for public employment agencies to sensitize workers on the importance of being better prepared for the labor market.
- Conducted in-field visits to compile best practices and challenges facing federal employment agencies.
- Delivered a training book on best practices to improve job matching between firms and workers and disseminated the findings to municipal and state secretariats of labor.
- Participated in high-level international workshops with research and government counterparts to disseminate the impacts of public policies on labor markets.
- Trained IADB employees at the Brasilia Country Office in econometrics and Stata.

GO ASSOCIADOS ECONOMIST

Jan 2013 - Apr 2014 | São Paulo, Brazil

- Analyzed the economic viability of public-private partnerships in education and infrastructure areas.
- Led the delivery of reports on market concentration impacts of firm mergers.

UNIVERSITY OF SÃO PAULO

IVBA PROGRAMMER

Jun 2011 - Dec 2012 | São Paulo, Brazil

- Developed macros in VBA to automatize the setup of descriptive statistics from a tourism survey conducted in Brazilian airports.
- The code allowed the creation of standardized tables that could be easily reproduced once a new survey wave was available.

JP MORGAN CHASE

INTERN OF THE ECONOMIC RESEARCH

DEPARTMENT.

Jan 2009 - Jan 2010 | São Paulo, Brazil

TEACHING ASSISTANCE

ECONOMETRICS I FOR UNDERGRAD STUDENTS

University of São Paulo (FEA-USP)

Jul 2011 - Dec 2011 | São Paulo, Brazil

ECONOMETRICS II FOR UNDERGRAD STUDENTS

| University of São Paulo (FEA-USP)

Feb 2012 - Jun 2012 | São Paulo, Brazil

AWARDS

DEVELOPMENT ECONOMICS VPU AWARD

WORLD BANK

Data and Analytics for Public Employment and Management, 2020

EQUITABLE GROWTH, FINANCE, AND INSTITUTIONS VPU AWARD

| World Bank

Comprehensive Modelling to Support Fiscal Sustainability/Brazil, 2019

HUMAN DEVELOPMENT VPU AWARD

WORLD BANK

A fair adjustment: efficiency and equity of public spending in Brazil, 2018

PUBLICATIONS AND WORKING PAPERS

THE SHORT AND LONGER-TERM EFFECTS OF A CHILD LABOR BAN

WITH CAIO PIZA, ANDRÉ PORTELA, AND PATRICK EMERSON

IZA Discussion Paper 2022 | Code to reproduce the results

LEARNING WHEN SCHOOLS SHUT DOWN: THE IMPACT OF THE H1N1 OUTBREAK ON PRIMARY EDUCATION STUDENTS IN BRAZIL

| WITH CAIO PIZA, AND ILDO LAUTHARTE

Preliminary Findings | Code to reproduce the results

EXPERIMENTAL EVIDENCE OF A FINANCIAL EDUCATION INTERVENTION TARGETING ELEMENTARY AND MIDDLE SCHOOL STUDENTS IN BRAZIL

WITH CAIO PIZA, AND ISABELA FURTADO.

Policy Research Working Paper 2023 | Code to reproduce the results

GESTÃO DE PESSOAS E FOLHA DE PAGAMENTOS NO SETOR PÚBLICO BRASILEIRO: O QUE OS DADOS DIZEM?

| WITH DANIEL ORTEGA, AND RAFAEL TAVARES

Brasília, Brazil. World Bank Group. 2019

LANGUAGES

Portuguese Native Speaker • Fluent English • Advanced Spanish

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING TOOLS/PLATFORMS

Proficient: Familiar:

• Stata • LATFX • Excel/VBA • R • Python • SQL • Git

REFERENCES

Caio Piza, Senior Economist, World BankD/DIME

□ caiopiza@worldbank.org

Christian Lehmann, Professor of Economics, University of Brasília

christianlehmann0@gmail.com